[Music]
so we've talked about this before but
stoicism is kind of undergoing
resurgence and I know you've written
quite a bit about stoicism in the past
right can you tell me about bit more
about that I know you've kind of linked
it to Silicon Valley and you've linked
it yeah and kind of almost like a
Western form of Buddhism right yeah so
stoicism kind of ancient Greek
philosophy it's very practical it was a
kind of form of therapy for the emotions
it has enjoyed an unlikely revival I
would say in the last 10 years the name
comes from the stoic point lay which is
called the painted colonnade which is a
kind of particular street in Athens they
would gather at each in the street so
it's kind of open streets philosophy the
idea of it is that we should live
according to nature and their definition
of nature's that were rational moral
beings so we should learn to develop our
reason and and our virtue and they
thought that would be enough to be happy
so they promised happiness all you need
to be happy is just to develop your
virtue that idea comes from Socrates and
basically you develop your virtue by not
being attached to externals or averse to
them so it's quite similar to Buddhism
and Daoism and so on in that respect
Seneca a stoic philosopher says the
stoic sees everything is training the
obstacle is the way so you lose your job
it's conventionally awful but for the
stoic it's actually potentially a moment
of profound awakening and and liberation
from from from conventional goods
similar to other spiritual traditions
really you get a terrible illness
conventionally is awful but it could be
morally and spiritually awakening and
this theory was the main inspiration for
cognitive behavioral therapy so it's one
of things I looked at my book
Albert Ellis the man who invented really
pioneered cognitive behavioral therapy
and Aaron Beck the other guy who
invented both were inspired by stoicism
and the stoic therapy of the emotions so
what the stoic says whenever you have a
powerful emotional reaction to something
it may feel involuntary and automatic
and beyond your control but actually all
emotions involve judgments and beliefs
you know like the judgment that's
terrifying and I'm going to die and
that's awful or the judgments you know
that's she's perfect and desirable and I
you know I must I must go out with her
or something like that and you can
actually look at the belief or judgment
underlying an emotion and say is that
definitely true is that definitely wise
do I definitely have to believe that and
so we have some control we don't always
have control over what happens to us but
we have some control over our beliefs
our opinions our interpretation of
things we can choose our perspective
Marcus Aurelius the stoic Empress said
life is but what you deem it life itself
is but what you deem it so we can choose
our perspective on the things that
happen to us and that will affect how we
feel so for example when I was younger I
had bad social anxiety crippling and
that was it felt like I messed myself up
on drugs and that this was something
neurochemical beyond my control and I
thought God is it going to be like this
for the rest of my life have I ruined my
life and maybe there's nothing I can do
about it apart from take beta blockers
or you know other drugs and then through
stoicism I realized actually this awful
anxiety and terror I feel is connected
to my beliefs and my values and my life
philosophy which was unconscious my
unconscious life philosophy which I got
grown up with and got for my family in
my school and Mike
was basically I must be approved of by
all people and if I don't it's a
disaster the mote you know that my value
is very much tight what other people
think of me and I grew up with terrible
showoff
and I loved making other people laugh
and impressing people and amassing
honors and glory so I had a an identity
extremely geared towards external
approval and the flip side of that was
was was with social anxiety and I kind
of and I thought God that I'm doing this
to myself through my own beliefs my own
unconscious automatic beliefs and you
know I could use the practice of
Stoicism to become aware of these
automatic unconscious beliefs this this
unconscious life philosophy was
completely shaping my reality and say
that's a dumb way to think you know
that's impossible you're never going to
get everyone to like you
it's an unwise philosophy so you can use
that you know you use the practice and
CBT in stores and they call it a
Socratic method why am I getting so
worked up about this what belief is
underlying this emotion is that belief
definitely true
why am i putting so much emphasis on
something that's beyond my control other
people's opinions and that's quite
fickle that just you know the stock
market of pulpit public opinions
constantly going up or down so if you
make that the basis of your self-esteem
you are never going to be stable or
happy why not bring it back to what's
within my control my own beliefs my own
opinions why not choose to accept myself
even if other people don't and what I
found was that once I started to follow
this this kind of different philosophy
it affected my emotions as well I
stopped having a panic attacks I stopped
feeling so anxious so yeah so stoicism
was extremely helpful to me
terms of kind of coming through that
anxiety and transforming my thoughts and
my beliefs and my emotions and my neuro
chemistry I mean it kind of changes your
kind of whole reality really how do you
know that it's become really popular now
and why do you think that is media
coverage for one thing it's so much more
common now to have articles about
stoicism it's it's I mean people don't
even have to say stoicism which by the
way is an ancient philosophy from Rome
people it's it's you hear it mentioned
so much more often in podcasts you see
more more famous people saying they're
into it from Darren Brown to Elle
McPherson who named her son after Marcus
Aurelius these are the things I see and
why now people feel out of control
stoicism says except that except you
can't control the external world but you
can find a measure of serenity and
happiness and moral meaning by focusing
on what is in your control your own
beliefs in your own actions it arose at
a time of great political turbulence
when the Greek city-states were being
conquered by marauding empires before
then Greek philosophers had always tied
the good life to the good Society
stoicism says you can have a good life
even in a bad society even admidst chaos
so quite good for our times as well
secondly because of the the familiarity
and popularity with cognitive therapy
millions and millions of people have
been helped by cognitive therapy or know
what it is whenever I do a talk on
stoicism I always say who has heard of
CBT it's always like probably over 50%
of people have now more and more people
are aware that's how much CBT owes to
stoicism both in its theory of the
emotions and in specific practices like
using a journal like using Max
like the Socratic method and so on so
stoicism seems to be a kind of rational
evidence-based theory that fits with
science it's a moral philosophy but it
kind of fits with science as well where
you live in a very skeptical time so
people like that you can use the
techniques of stoicism whether you
believe in God or not so it's very
popular with atheists and skeptics or
with people who like Miam or kind of
more like theistic plus it's it's from
Western culture so that's interesting
you know it kind of gives you a way into
this wonderful tradition going back to
Socrates going through Shakespeare whose
variant esterases and going through
Montaigne going through the
Enlightenment philosophers you know it's
part of a way we we've had to turn to
things like Tibetan Buddhism or Peruvian
shamanism which are awesome traditions
but we can also find these things in our
own culture and have a connection to
2,000 years of Western culture so that's
amazing as well you mentioned before
that it's sort of Silicon Valley is
somewhere that seems quite aligned with
it I'm thinking I don't know if Tim
Ferriss has ever talked specifically
about stoicism did its head to a clinic
yeah when I think of Tim Ferriss I think
yeah there's a real stoic kind of
quality to a modern what he's talking
about I didn't know he'd actually done a
specific talk about it yeah well
stoicism in a way is quite a neat tidy
philosophy for if you have an
engineering mind and you want algorithms
for life let Darren brown say the thing
he loves about stem is a clear thing is
this in my control or not you know if no
accept it if you get quite you know
anxious about uncertainty or ambiguity
this is a clear algorithm so engineers
love it for that reason
entrepreneurs love it because they have
to deal with so much uncertainty they
don't know we know this has been kind of
entrepreneurial ourselves you know
you status volatility you don't know if
you're if you're if your brilliant idea
is going to take off and you're going to
be you know a massive hit or if it's
going to kind of slump and you might
have experiences tastes of both so so
entrepreneurs have to deal with that
like from going to feeling like a god to
a kind of nobody
and so stoicism gives them a way to help
them find a sense of security inner
security and inner meaning that is not
dependent on that stock market of public
opinion and it helps them deal with risk
and the fear of failure and so I think
that's why Tim Ferriss is particularly
into it his his TED talks on using
stoicism to cope with the fear of
failure and plus of course Stoics
ancient Stoics were not ascetics
they were people of the world like
Seneca was both the stoic and one of the
richest men in the Roman Empire Marcus
Aurelius probably had a few Bob as well
yeah yeah he was that he was the emperor
of Rome so yeah if you're out in the
world as well this is in a way a
philosophy in a detachment but not of
going off to a cave or becoming a monk
so in some ways it kind of fits with
Western society more obviously than
Buddhism which was a mania philosophy
for ascetics for monks seems very
Christian influenced but stoicism
predates Christianity yeah I know
Christianity is stoic influenced so
what's the common ancestor if there is a
common ancestor Christianity is directly
influenced by stoicism and by Greek
philosophy stoic Greek Christianity is a
mash up of Judaism and Greek philosophy
so the Gospel of John says Jesus is the
logos made flesh which is a great idea
in a way you know because Greek
philosophy has this idea of the divine
but it's a rather intellectual
abstract principle and Christianity says
okay you know that that's a person who
died for you and you know as Hinduism
found Hinduism did something similar
with the Bhagavad Gita before that had
this idea of the Brahman this
intellectual principle it's a bit
difficult to really love that inflation
principle so they said yes and and you
know that's actually Krishna this this
this wonderful being so the
bhagavad-gita was taking that kind of
abstract intellectual monotheism of via
Panna shirts and turning into a much
more of a devotional thing centered on
him on a person but yeah the early you
know Christianity is deeply influenced
by Greek philosophy and by stoicism the
early Christian fathers were really
literate on Greek philosophy Augustine
was a neoplatonist before he's a
Christian and he took loads of his
Neoplatonism with him later christian
medusa mystics like st. Teresa of Avila
her nickname for some John of the Cross
who who kind of lived with him was my
little Seneca yes so Nietzsche said that
Christianity is just Platonism for the
masses but there's there's there's all
kinds of similarities and in fact when I
was a Christian briefly and I thought
was a real pity that modern Christians
don't have that awareness of of Greek
philosophy because it's really great
practical wisdom you know in the modern
church if you have problems the only
therapy solution is basically to
surrender to Jesus more they've lost all
those practical exercises there's
practical psychological techniques which
earlier Christians had partly through
kind of Greek philosophy but I remember
having to give a testimony at an
evangelical church and they said and I
told them about this near-death
experience I had
they said and did that lead you to Jesus
I said no let me to Greek philosophy and
there was this awful kind of silence in
the church because anything that's not
Jesus is often the kind of seen as
suspicious and possibly demonic in
modern church rather than this kind of
generalist you know pluralism where in
earlier times in Christian history they
would say I mean set yes Socrates in
Seneca were pretty much worshipped to
Saints in the Middle Ages yeah they were
seen as almost kind of prophets